Guide to the New York City Central Labor Council Records WAG.049
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York City Central Labor Council Records
1933-2019
1970-2018
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council
WAG.049
306.50 Linear Feet in 294 record cartons and 22 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 flat box, and 4 oversize folders in shared housing.
8 videocassettes (vhs)
2 videocassettes (minidv)
2.09 Gigabytes
4 websites in 4 archived websites.
The collection consists of records of the New York City Central Labor Council (founded, after a merger with the New York City CIO Council, in 1959) as well as some files, including minutes, of its predecessor organization, the Central Trades and Labor Council of Greater New York (chartered in 1920). For the later period (from 1960) the collection includes General Files and extensive files of individual officers of the Council. Files for the 1980s and 1990s are mainly from the offices of Council Secretary Ted H. Jacobsen and Council President Brian M. McLaughlin. They include reference material, reports, correspondence, flyers and copies of proposed legislation on a wide range of topics of concern to the labor movement: housing, health care, safety issues in the workplace, immigrant rights, political campaigns and matters relating to collective bargaining rights. There are also files on the various ethnic labor committees created by the Council beginning in the early 1970s and files on negotiations, strikes and disputes involving individual unions affiliated to the Council. There are files of organizational work for the annual Labor Day parade, march, and mass, which includes permits, meeting notes, promotional material, and financial materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the New York City Central Labor Council in several installments, 1986. The accession number associated with this gift is 1986.042.
The materials that comprise Boxes 290 and 291 were found in the repository in 2014. The accession number associated with these materials is 2014.120.
The New York City Central Labor Council donated an accretion in February 2020. The accession number associated with this gift is 2020.019.
https://www.nycclc.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. In 2015, this website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2021, http://www.workingtogether.nyc/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2021.089. In July 2021, https://www.climatejobsny.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.008. In August 2023, http://laborvotes.nyc/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.071.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical Note
The New York City Central Labor Council had its origins in the Central Trades and Labor Council of Greater New York City, chartered in 1920 by the American Federation of Labor (AFL). The Council represented AFL-affiliated local unions in the New York City area. After the split between the AFL and the newly-formed Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in the mid-1930s, CIO unions in the city were represented by a separate CIO Council. The Central Trades and Labor Council merged with the New York City CIO on February 19, 1959 to form the New York City Central Labor Council, AFL-CIO. This move followed the 1955 national merger of the AFL and the CIO, and the 1958 merger of New York state-level AFL and CIO bodies.
The New York City Central Labor Council is an organization comprised of nearly 400 local union affiliates. It only acts on local activities and concerns. It issues no statements on AFL-CIO policy and does not participate in the affairs of its local affiliates or their parent organizations. Its purpose, according to its constitution, is to further the rights of workers to organize in unions and bargain collectively; to advocate legislation which is beneficial to workers and oppose that which is not; to correct abuses and to insure the workers their just rights. It also has the broader purposes of helping all workers to improve their working conditions and raise their standard of living; to preserve workers' rights to act together for mutual aid and advancement; to further the cause of trade unions; and to strengthen civil rights. It acts as the central body of the City's labor movement, providing assistance and education through its various committees and councils.
The regular activities of the New York City Central Labor Council are directed by its executive officers, Executive Board, and Delegates' Council meetings. The planning and execution of programs and conferences is the province of a number of standing and special committees. These committees are composed of members from affiliated local unions, and each has its own officers and advisory staff. And is responsible for conducting specific programs and conferences. An important special committee is the Labor Day Parade Committee.
Harry Van Arsdale, Business Manager of International Brotherhood of Electricians Local 3, was elected the president of the Central Trades and Labor Council of the AFL in 1957. With the merger in 1959 he became the president of the Central Labor Council. During his presidency (1957-1986), the council established many committees and programs such as the Rehabilitation Council (1963), Hispanic Labor Committee (1970), and the Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee (1972). After Harry Van Arsdale Jr.'s death in 1986, his son, Thomas Van Arsdale was elected to the post of president. During the Van Arsdales' tenure the Council campaigned to organize taxicab drivers, helped to found a worker education program (the Harry Van Arsdale, Jr. Center for Labor Studies at Empire State College, SUNY), mobilized the labor movement to confront the City's fiscal crisis of the late 1970s, and generally worked to foster a spirit of solidarity throughout the many disparate sectors of the New York City labor movement
Thomas Van Arsdale was succeeded as president by Brian M. McLaughlin, also of IBEW Local 3, in 1995; and Gary LaBarbera of the Teamsters union was elected to replace McLaughlin in June 2007, with Ed Ott serving in the newly created position of Executive Director.
The Council's web site is http://www.nycclc.org/
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes some records (including minutes) of the Council's predecessor organization, the Central Trades and Labor Council of Greater New York. For the later period (from 1960) the collection includes General Files and extensive files of individual officers of the Council. Files for the 1980s and 1990s are mainly from the offices of Council Secretary Ted H. Jacobsen and Council President Brian M. McLaughlin. They include reference material, reports, correspondence, flyers and copies of proposed legislation on a wide range of topics of concern to the labor movement: housing, health care, safety issues in the workplace, immigrant rights, political campaigns and matters relating to collective bargaining rights. There are also files on the various ethnic labor committees created by the Council beginning in the early 1970s and files on negotiations, strikes and disputes involving individual unions affiliated to the Council. There are files of organizational work for the annual Labor Day parade, march, and mass, which includes permits, meeting notes, promotional material, and financial materials.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York City Labor Council, Minutes, 1933-1982 (Microfilm: Reels 7419/1-7)
Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee Records (WAG 138)
New York City Central Labor Council Photographs (PHOTOS 020)
Arrangement
This is an unprocessed collection; most sections are in original order, as received. Many boxes contain subject files arranged alphabetically within a given year (1995, A-D, etc.).
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact [repository name, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Clippings (information artifacts); Fliers (printed matter); Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activity; Labor movement -- New York (State) -- New York -- History; Reports.; Correspondence.; New York (N.Y.).; Strikes and lockouts.; Parades & processions.; May Day (Labor holiday).; Labor Day.; McLaughlin, Brian M.; Central Trades and Labor Council of Greater New York; AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council. Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee; Jacobsen, Ted H.; Van Arsdale, Harry, 1905-1986; Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee; AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council
- NYCCLC: Advisory Council Minutes (1973-1978); NYCCLC: Executive Board Minutes (1983-1985); AFL-CIO to China (1991), 1973-1991 (Box 1)
- Anti-Apartheid to CUNY, 1991 (Box 2)
- Delegate Entitlement and Voting Strength to United Way. Includes Domsey Strike: ILGWU, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
- General Files, 1990 (Box 4)
- General Files, 1990 (Box 5)
- Charter Revision to Circular Letters (1990); General Files (1993), 1990-1993 (Box 6)
- General Files; Unions: Engineers to Unions: Steelworkers, 1995 (Box 7)
- Unions: Actors to Unions: Electronic; Unions: Roofers to Unions: Writers Guild, 1995 (Box 8)
- General Files (1994); Union Locals Files (1995), 1994-1995 (Box 9)
- General Files, 1959-1968 (Box 10)
- General Files, 1958-1972 (Box 11)
- Taxi Drivers Organizing Committee, 1964-1966 (Box 12)
- Circular Letters to Transportation Bond Issue (1967); AFL-CIO to Con Edison Project (1968), 1967-1968 (Box 13)
- AFL-CIO to Newark Teachers' Strike, 1972 (Box 14)
- National Advisory Council on Economic Opportunity to Workmen's Circle, 1972 (Box 15)
- General Files, 1967 (Box 16)
- General Files (1966); General Files (1967), 1966-1967 (Box 17)
- General Central Labor Council to Voter Registration, 1965 (Box 18)
- AFL-CIO to TDOC, 1966 (Box 19)
- General Files (includes Transit Strike), 1966 (Box 20)
- Iushewitz, Morris, 1967-1974 (Box 21)
- General Files (mostly Van Arnsdale, Harry), 1965-1966 (Box 22)
- Board of Education Activities (1966); Merger of CIO Council (1950s); Performing Arts (1950s-1960s) (Box 23)
- Taft-Hartley (1959); Elections (1970-1979), 1959, 1970-1979 (Box 24)
- Red Cross to US Savings Bonds (1976); AFL-CIO to NYC-based International Presidents (1977), 1976-1977 (Box 25)
- AFL-CIO to Job Placement Program, 1978 (Box 26)
- Criminal Justice Coordinating Committee to Veterans' Affairs, 1975 (Box 27)
- General Files (includes Farah Strike), 1974 (Box 28)
- Mayor's Office for Veterans' Affairs to US Savings Bonds (1974); General Files (1975), 1974-1975 (Box 29)
- General Files (mostly Van Arsdale, Harry), 1975 (Box 30)
- American Arbitration Association to Public Development Corporation, 1974 (Box 31)
- International Brotherhood Of Electrical Workers, Local 3 to Workmens' Compensation (1973); AFL-CIO (1974), 1973-1974 (Box 32)
- General Files (includes Farah Strike), 1973 (Box 33)
- Arsdale, Harry Van to Labor Studies, 1972 (Box 34)
- General Files, 1974 (Box 35)
- AFL-CIO/COPE to Local Union Correspondence, 1973 (Box 36)
- General Files, 1969 (Box 37)
- Carnegie Hall to Van Arsdale, Harry, 1968 (Box 38)
- American Foundation on Automation and Employment to Workers' Compensation (1970); Van Arsdale, Harry (1971), 1970-1971 (Box 39)
- American Arbitration Association to Public Development Corporation, 1976 (Box 40)
- General Files (includes J.P. Stevens Boycott), 1977 (Box 41)
- Circular Letters to Van Arsdale, Harry, 1978 (Box 42)
- AFL-CIO to New York City Central Labor Council Executive Board, 1976 (Box 43)
- American Arbitration Association to Van Arsdale, Harry, 1977 (Box 44)
- AFL-CIO to Local Union Correspondence, 1979 (Box 45)
- Advisory Council to Strikes, 1975 (Box 46)
- General Files, 1977 (Box 47)
- General Files, 1978 (Box 48)
- AFL-CIO to United Way/United Fund; Van Arsdale, Harry, 1980 (Box 49)
- AFL-CIO to Local Union Correspondence, 1981 (Box 50)
- AFL-CIO to Lincoln's Birthday Dinner, 1982 (Box 51)
- AFL-CIO to Human Resources; Reisel, Victor to Workmen's Compensation, 1971 (Box 52)
- Blue Cross (AHS) to Strikes, 1971 (Box 53)
- American Arbitration Association to Public Development Corporation, 1971 (Box 54)
- General Files, 1970 (Box 55)
- AFL-CIO to Non-partisan: Richmond, 1970 (Box 56)
- Iushewitz, Morris (1968); Office of Collective Bargaining to Workmen's Compensation (1968); AFL-CIO to Demonstration Project (1969), 1968-1969 (Box 57)
- General files: A-R (1960s); Labor Day Files (1970s), 1960s-1970s (Box 58)
- General Files (includes Local Union Correspondence), 1968 (Box 59)
- Circular Letters to Strikes (includes General Electric Strike), 1969 (Box 60)
- Local 174: Strike, Hebrew National to Van Arsdale, Harry, School of Labor Studies, 1986 (Box 61)
- Advisory Council for Occupational Education to Communications Workers of America Strike vs. AT&T, 1986 (Box 62)
- General Files, 1986-1987 (Box 63)
- CIO newspaper clippings and counselor's manual (1945-1952); New York City Central Labor Council Community Services documents (1960s); Business/Labor Working Group documents and reports (1970s); Labor Day Poster (1983), 1945-1983 (Box 64)
- General Files (includes PATCO Strike), 1981 (Box 65)
- Advisory Council to Van Arsdale, Harry, 1980 (Box 66)
- AFL-CIO to Public Employees Committee, 1980 (Box 67)
- General files: includes Polish Solidarity, 1982 (Box 68)
- General files, 1987 (Box 69)
- Miscellaneous to Van Arsdale, Harry, 1979 (Box 70)
- Labor Day Parade Master Book (1959); Taxi Drivers (1965-1978); Labor Day Parade (1982-1985), 1959-1985 (Box 71)
- Appointment Books, Organizational, 1961-1983 (Box 72)
- Van Arsdale, Harry;AFL-CIO Mortgage Investing to US Savings Bonds, 1984 (Box 73)
- General files: includes numerous files on boycotts, rallies, and strikes, plus Mondale/Ferraro Campaign, 1984-1987 (Box 74)
- General Files (includes Van Arsdale, Thomas), 1992 (Box 75)
- General Files, 1994-1995 (Box 76)
- General Files, 1994 (Box 77)
- General Files: includes Clinton/Gore Election Campaign, 1992 (Box 78)
- Jacobsen, Ted to Labor/Management, 1994 (Box 79)
- Delegates/Credentials to Resumes, 1992 (Box 80)
- No Union Label/Bug/Hotel to Political, 1994 (Box 81)
- Association for a Better NY to Dompsey;Visitors to Workers' Memorial Day, 1992 (Box 82)
- Black Trade Unionists Leadership to Naval, 1994 (Box 83)
- General Files (mostly AFL-CIO), 1992 (Box 84)
- Advisory Council for Occupational Education to Alcoholism, 1987 (Box 85)
- AFL-CIO 1987 Regional Conferences to Committee for Public Higher Education (1987);Frontlash to Greyhound (1990), 1987, 1990 (Box 86)
- Advisory Council to Delegates, 1987-1988 (Box 87)
- Labor News to Strikes and Boycotts, 1988 (Box 88)
- General Files, 1988 (Box 89)
- General Files: includes Labor Day Parade (1984, 1987, 1989), 1984-1989 (Box 90)
- General Files, 1986 (Box 91)
- Certificate of Affiliation with CIO (1949); General Files (1986), 1949, 1986 (Box 92)
- Consumers Assembly to Jacobsen, Ted: Personal, 1987 (Box 93)
- Cornell University to Van Arsdale, Harry, 1985 (Box 94)
- Lincoln's Birthday to New York City Central Labor Council: Telephone Systems, 1987 (Box 95)
- NY State AFL-CIO to Unions: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1987 (Box 96)
- Greyhound to Irish-American, 1990 (Box 97)
- Labor Day (1968, 1983); Tax Records (1980-1989); Union Label and Service Trades Department Records (1987-1995), 1968-1995 (Box 98)
- Commercial Rents to NY State Financial Control Board, 1988 (Box 99)
- Unions: Teamsters to world Rehabilitation Fund, 1988 (Box 100)
- Jacobsen, Ted, 1987 (Box 101)
- General files, 1972-1976 (Box 102)
- Audio tapes of various meetings (1987-1988);Business cards and political and union buttonsGeneral files: mostly AFL-CIO (1990), 1987-1988, 1990 (Box 103)
- Labor Day, 1968, 1981, 1983 (Box 104)
- General files, 1976-1982 (Box 105)
- Telefaxes, 1988-1989 (Box 106)
- General files, 1988 (Box 107)
- General files: includes Parking Meter and Street Lighting, 1979-1986 (Box 108)
- Accountant to Central America, 1990 (Box 109)
- Unions: Bakery Confectionery & Tobacco Workers to Unions: Operating Engineers;General files: includes Daily News Boycott, 1990 (Box 110)
- US Dept. of Labor to Workers Memorial Day;General files: mostly AFL-CIO, 1993 (Box 111)
- AFL-CIO to Constitution, 1988 (Box 112)
- South America to Van Arsdale, Harry: Labor College, 1989 (Box 113)
- Housing Now to Labor Day Parade, 1989 (Box 114)
- Labor Department, Friends of the, to NYCCLC Asian Labor Committee, 1989 (Box 115)
- General files; NYCCLC Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee to Picketing, 1989 (Box 116)
- NYCCLC Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1951-1982 (Box 117)
- General files: includes Brian McLaughlin, 1987-1988 (Box 118)
- NY State Labor History Association to Unions: Miscellaneous, 1988 (Box 119)
- Constitution to Legislation, 1988 (Box 120)
- Women to Xerox (1989); NAACP to NY State AFL-CIO Convention (1990), 1989-1990 (Box 121)
- Circular Letters to Foreign Visitors, 1990 (Box 122)
- Adopt-a-School to Consortium for Workers Education, 1989 (Box 123)
- Consumer Assembly to Hotel and Motel Trades Union, 1989 (Box 124)
- Shared Work to Unions: Daily News, 1990 (Box 125)
- Jacobsen, Ted to Labor Institute of Public Affairs, 1990 (Box 126)
- Union Label to Unions: Automobile Workers Union (1991)Irish-American to Jacobsen, Ted (1992), 1991-1992 (Box 127)
- General files, 1993 (Box 128)
- AFL-CIO 1993 campaigns manualGeneral files (1999), 1993, 1999 (Box 129)
- United Way to Youth Employment;Various others, 1990 (Box 130)
- General files, 1990 (Box 131)
- European Community to Invitations, 1992 (Box 132)
- LRLP News Clippings, 1963-1967 (Box 133)
- General files: includes Union locals files, 1990 (Box 134)
- Unions: Daily News to Unions: Stage Employees, 1990 (Box 135)
- Prison Labor to Unions: Graphic Communications, 1993 (Box 136)
- Political Committees to South Africa, 1995 (Box 137)
- General files: mostly AFL-CIO (1989); School Construction Authority to Unemployment (1993) (Box 138)
- General files, 1995 (Box 139)
- General files, 1988-1989 (Box 140)
- General files, 1989-1990, 1995 (Box 141)
- General files (1989);Safety and Health to Union Label (1995), 1989, 1995 (Box 142)
- General files, 1988, 1990, 1994 (Box 143)
- General files, 1990 (Box 144)
- General files: mostly AFL-CIO. Includes photos., 1995 (Box 145)
- Daily News (1990); Van Arsdale, Thomas: Appointments (1990-1991)US Department of Labor to Visitors (1995), 1990-1991, 1995 (Box 146)
- Unfiled papers, 1994 (Box 147)
- US Senate to Train Delays (1992);BNA Reports (1995);Van Arsdale, Harry: Memorial Association (1995), 1992, 1995 (Box 148)
- General files, 1991 (Box 149)
- Van Arsdale, Thomas to United Way, 1992 (Box 150)
- Legislation to NYCCLC, 1992 (Box 151)
- Labor Day Parade to NYCCLC: Advisory Council, 1992 (Box 152)
- Unions: AFSCME to United Way, 1992 (Box 153)
- Delegate Entitlement and Voting Strength to Employment;Lincoln's Birthday to Miscellaneous, 1992 (Box 154)
- Eastern to Frontlash (1991); United Way of NY (1995), 1991, 1995 (Box 155)
- Haiti to International Labor Communications Association (1991);Future Reference to King, Martin Luther, Jr. (1992), 1991-1992 (Box 156)
- AFL-CIO Union Privilege Benefits to Legislation (General), 1995 (Box 157)
- Religion to Telefax: Charles Michaelson (1992);Pride of Judea (1993);Unions: Hotel and Restaurant Employees to Unions: Steelworkers, 1992-1993 (Box 158)
- Labor Day to Labor Leaders/Labor History, 1995 (Box 159)
- AFL-CIO Community Services to Circular Letters, 1994 (Box 160)
- General files, 1995 (Box 161)
- Unions: United Staff Association (NYU) to Unions: Writers Guild, 1993 (Box 162)
- General files, 1991 (Box 163)
- Invitations to Jacobsen, Ted, 1991 (Box 164)
- General files: includes Brian McLaughlin, 1991 (Box 165)
- General files: includes Jacobsen, Ted, 1992 (Box 166)
- Environment to Jacobsen, Ted, 1995 (Box 167)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1968-1970 (Box 168)
- Gay/Lesbian to Italian Hospital Society (1993);Asian to Building and Construction Trades (1995), 1993, 1995 (Box 169)
- Family to Free Trade Agreement, 1993 (Box 170)
- Bond Act to Consumer Assembly, 1992 (Box 171)
- Dinkins, David to Dislocated Workers (1992);AFL-CIO Union Privilege Benefits to Black (1995), 1992, 1995 (Box 172)
- Fax to Italian American, 1993 (Box 173)
- Free Trade Agreement to Health; Safety and Health, 1993 (Box 174)
- Histadrut to Jacobsen, Ted: Oldtimers, 1995 (Box 175)
- Budget to Disabled, 1995 (Box 176)
- AFL-CIO to Consumers Assembly, 1995 (Box 177)
- Italian to Jacobsen, Ted: School-to-Work, 1995 (Box 178)
- I Paid My Dues, (musical): Scrapbooks (1976); Newspaper clippings (1975-1977) (Box 179)
- Newspaper clippings (1971-1975); Correspondence scrapbook (1973-1974) (Box 180)
- General files: includes Van Arsdale, Harry, 1963 (Box 181)